I'm going to talk about how to write C++ that's safe for
some definition of safety.
And the general idea is, what is safety?
What kind of safety are there?
What do we need?
That's the first quarter.
Then I'm going to show you that we've been creeping up on that
for a few decades.
It's part of the initial aims of C++.
Then I'm going to talk about how to write good contemporary C++
under the label of the C++ core guidelines.
And then I'm going to talk about profiles,
which is about how to guarantee safety.
Because guidelines and
being careful is not sufficient in all areas.
So one of the reasons there's so much talk about safety
is that parts of the US government started going on about safety,
which is quite reasonable.
But they're talking about the whole community,
which may or may not be true.
And they're talking about the mythical language C, C++,
which I have something to say about.
Anyway, you can look it up.
This is a serious concern that we have to deal with.
On the other hand, there's no reason to panic.
C++ is doing well in general thing.
I mean, TOB measures noise, not usage.
So these numbers doesn't show precisely anything.
But it does show that maybe a billion or
two people depend on what we are doing, so we better do it well.
So we have to address the safety issue.
It's a real serious problem.
I mean, I really don't want my brakes not to work when I press it,
if I had a car.
And there are other things, if you're in financials,
you don't want a transaction to disappear,
especially if it was going into your account.
And so there's a lot of aspects of this.
And the interesting thing is that massive improvement really
is possible in a lot of areas.
One of my messages in this talk is don't write C slash C++, write C++.
We can do much, much better than some of the problems that has been documented.
And well, if we don't do it, somebody else will tell us what to do,
and we'll like that even less.
So ignoring safety issues would hurt the community.
And offering guaranteed safety would be in the best tradition of C++, so
this is actually an opportunity.
I mean, don't let a problem stop you from doing something good.
So the ideal of complete type and
resource safety wasn't C++ from the beginning.
Simula was one of the completely safe languages, except for the bugs.
Simula was pretty good at breaking it.
But one thing that we know is that
we couldn't have complete safety with the hardware we had then and
we can't now for all languages and for all uses.
But being careful doesn't scare.
So we have to use judicious programming techniques supported by library,
enforced by language rules and analysis.
And I wrote up a basic model for how to do that a few years ago.
I actually presented it here, but not much happened.
We need it to be C++.
That is, there shouldn't be restrictions on what we can do,
even though there might be restrictions on how we do it.
And there shouldn't be any decline in performance.
So this is C++ and
actually some of the techniques for writing safe codes improve performance.
I'm talking mostly about what can be done by a compiler on static checking
because it is free or actually gives improvements in performance.
But of course, you need range checking to deal with things that
cannot be dealt with statically.
And so basically, I'm talking about type and resource safety.
And I think this is pretty well defined.
Every object is accessed according to the type with which it was defined.
That's type safety.
And every object is properly constructed and destroyed.
Resource safety, you can manage resources that way.
If you don't initialize things, then you're breaking some rule.
And every pointer either points to a valid object or is a null pointer.
That's memory safety.
That's harder to achieve, but we can do it.
And a reference through a pointer is not through the null pointer.
That is, we have to check for
null pointers before we go and dereference these valid pointers.
And access through a subscripted pointer is in range.
That requires a runtime check, and I'll get to that.
So basically, this is just what the rules require.
You read the standard, and that's what it requires.
Read Denny's 45-page C manual from 78, that's what it requires.
It's just we haven't been doing it.
And so the rules I'm putting forward here are more deduced
than invented.
They're deduced for what it takes to do what's on this slide.
And enforcement rules that I'm suggesting are mutually dependent.
You can't just take one thing out of context and
expect to get easily specified benefit out of it.
You have to have a framework for
what you are doing to see what you are planning to get out of it.
And C++ still has to serve a wide variety of users and areas.
We have millions of users and billions of people relying on us.
And one size doesn't fit all.
We can't just say this is what safety is, everybody do it this way.
That doesn't quite work.
C++ is also a systems programming.
We manipulate hardware in various ways.
We use unusual hardware that is not known in language specification.
And we can't outsource this to other languages.
A lot of the so-called safe languages outsource all the low-level stuff to
C or C++.
So if we couldn't do it, well, there would be C left, and
basically, but somebody has to do the dirty job here.
And we can't break billions of lines of existing code.
I say can't, not shouldn't, because we can't.
If we try, people will use the old compilers,
they will go to a different subset, they will just ignore us.
This can't be done.
And we can't upgrade the millions of developers quickly.
It takes a long time.
I keep bumping into people who learn C++ from videos and
books that are 10 or 20 years old.
I mean, it's tragic, but it could have been so much easier, and
the result could have been so much better if they had up-to-date
materials teaching up-to-date C++.
But getting a whole community like this to move forward
is much harder than most people imagine.
Okay, these are difficulties, but we must improve, and we can.
So the challenge is to describe what we mean by type safe C++ use,
no violations to the static type system, no resource leak.
If a system leaks a resource, memory, locks, file handles and
such, I wouldn't consider it safe, because I can crash it with
the equivalent of denial of service attack.
Or I could just be sloppy and
it crashes when it runs out of resources.
So I'm very keen on resource safety, and this is actually one
of the things that came into C++ in the first two weeks.
And we have to convince developers to do this.
There's a lot of belief out there that if you do grubby,
complicated, low-level stuff, it must be faster.
And furthermore, I can write this grubby,
low-level, complicated stuff to show how smart I am.
This does not work.
We have to raise the level of programming and get this to work at scale.
I mean, if I have a class of students.